Okay today's דף *Daf* is דף מ"ו *Daf Mem Vav* בבא קמא
*Bava Kama* 46. We pick up at the bottom of מ"ה עמוד
ב' *Mem Hey Amud Bet* and אמר רב *Amar Rav*, it is
one two three five lines from the bottom. רב *Rav*, אמר רב
*Amar Rav*. That's and our learning should be in the merit of
the protection of all of our חיילים *chayalim* and חיילות *chayalot* and
the hostages and everybody who's in harm's way. All right אמר רב
מועד muad לקרן ימין אינו מועד muad, לקרן שמאל *Amar Rav muad
le-keren yamin eno muad le-keren smol*. So we just got through a
whole discussion about the level of שמירה shmira. *shemira* required for a
תם tam *tam* and a מועד muad. *muad* and רבי מאיר *Rebbi
Meir*, we're focusing now on the positions of רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir*
and רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda*. רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* says that both
a תם tam *tam* and a מועד muad *muad* require שמירה shmira
מעולה *shemira meula*, a high level of שמירה shemira *shemira* to be
exempt. And רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* has the ironic position that a
מועד muad. *muad* requires a low level of שמירה *shemira* and a
תם tam *tam* requires a high level. And now רב *Rav* is
saying if an animal became a מועד muad. *muad* for its right
horn it is not a מועד muad, *muad* for its left horn.
So an animal gored three times and all three times used its
right horn, it is not a מועד muad, *muad* for its left
horn. Now as רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* and תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* both point
out that's רב *Rav* doesn't need to tell us that as a
general principle, meaning we already we have a lot of discussion in
משניות *Mishnayos* and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that if an animal is
מועד muad, *muad* for one thing they're not מועד *muad* for another
thing. If they're מועד *muad* for goring, you know cows, they're not
מועד *muad* for goring sheep. A lot of types of distinctions like
that and certainly if they're מועד *muad* for goring with a right
horn, assuming that's I don't know if animals favor their right side
as well, anyway then it would not be מועד *muad* for goring
its left horn just cause it gores with its right we should
not assume that it's habitual to gore with its left. So that
idea that if it gores with its left it will only pay
half damages, that's obvious. That can't be what רב *Rav* is coming
to tell us. So the assumption is that what רב *Rav* is
coming to tell us has something to do with the issue of
שמירה *shemira*. Okay? That if somehow there's a case in which because
of this there's a difference between right horn and left horn that
you could watch, you could do a certain level of שמירה *shemira*
and be חייב chayav *chayav* for one of the horns and not
the other. Okay let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. אמרי אליבא דמאן *Amri
aliba de-man* according to whom is רב *Rav* telling us this idea
that it's interesting to think of right horn and left horn in
terms of שמירה *shemira*. אי אליבא דרבי מאיר *Ei aliba de-Rebbi Meir*
האמר אחד תם tam ואחד מועד שמירה
מעולה בעי *ha'amar echad tam ve-echad
muad shemira meula ba'i*.
So according to רבי מאיר *Rebbi Meir* if you did they're תם
*tam* and מועד *muad* have the same level high level of שמירה
*shemira*. So if you did only a low level you're חייב chayav.
*chayav* both for the right horn and the left horn. And if
you did a high level you're פטור *patur* for both. אלא אי
אליבא דרבי יהודה *Ela ei aliba de-Rebbi Yehuda*. Now if it's according
to רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* so מאי אירייא קרן שמאל אפילו בימין
נמי אית ביה צד תמות *mai irya keren smol afilu be-yamin nami
it bei tzad tamus*. I skipped a line. I skipped a line.
אי אליבא דרבי מאיר *Ei aliba de-Rebbi Meir* I skipped a line.
אי אליבא דרבי יהודה *Ei aliba de-Rebbi Yehuda* now if it's according
to רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* so מאי אירייא קרן שמאל אפילו בימין
נמי אית ביה צד תמות *mai irya keren smol afilu be-yamin nami
it bei tzad tamus*. So you could say it's interesting to think
about this according to רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda*. You did a low
level of שמירה *shemira*. Now it's for that works for the right
horn, that works for the מועד *muad* part of the animal, but
it doesn't work for the תם *tam*. So if you do a
low level of שמירה *shemira* and it goes out and gores with
its right horn you're exempt, ironically. And if it gores with its
left horn you're going to be חייב chayav *chayav* because it's a
מועד *muad* for the right and it's a תם *tam* for the
left. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says but one minute, according to
רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* you could have that cute idea without even
introducing another horn. Why? Because רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* says, because
even in the right horn you could have that it would gore
with the right and you would be חייב chayav? *chayav* half damages
why נמי אית ביה צד תמות ואית ביה צד מועדות *nami it
bei tzad tamus ve-it bei tzad muadus*. So רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda*
remember we have argued that says that צד תמות במקומה עומדת tzad
tamus bimkomah omedes. *tzad tamus be-mekoma omedes*. So for רבי יהודה *Rebbi
Yehuda* even if it you just focus on the right horn and
you do a minimum שמירה *shemira* and it goes out and gores
you'll be חייב chayav? *chayav* half damages because of the תם *tam*
part of the right horn. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says אמרי
לעולם כרבי יהודה *Amri le-olam ke-Rebbi Yehuda*. You're right we are going
like רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* because that's the only way you'll have
an interesting difference of a level of שמירה *shemira* that will still
retain an obligation for the תם *tam* side. ולא סבירא ליה דרב
אדא בר אהבה *Velo sevira lei de-Rav Adda bar Ahava*. But he
doesn't hold of שמואל *Shmuel* I'm sorry not who is this one
who said this רב *Rav* doesn't hold of רב אדא בר אהבה
*Rav Adda bar Ahava*. He doesn't hold of this principle of צד
תמות במקומה עומדת *tzad tamus be-mekoma omedes*. Once an animal becomes a
מועד *muad* they're a full מועד *muad*. Okay? And you only treat
it in the מועד *muad* capacity. והכי קאמר *Ve-hachi ka'amar* and here's
what he is saying. He's really responding to רב אדא בר אהבה
*Rav Adda bar Ahava*. כי האי גוונא הוא דמשכחת צד תמות ומועדות
*Ki hai gavna hu de-mishkachat tzad tamus u-muadus*. If you do he
says look you רב אדא בר אהבה *Rav Adda bar Ahava* you
have this idea that if an animal is a מועד *muad* for
רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda*
there's always going to be a half מועד *muad* half תם *tam*.
And if you do a low level of שמירה *shemira* and it
grows out then even for an animal that's a full מועד *muad*
or whatever you do a low level of שמירה *shemira* you're still
חייב chayav. *chayav* for the half תם *tam* that's part of it.
And to that רב *Rav* says I don't buy that. Once an
animal's a
מועד *muad*... Do you want to know a scenario where a low
level of שמירה you’ll still be חייב chayav for half and not
for the other half? I could understand that if you had a
right horn and a left horn. A right horn and a left
horn. It was מועד for the right, and it was תם for
the left. That would be a case that you did a low
level of שמירה. If it gored with the right you’re exempt, if
it gored with the left, you’re חייב. Okay, אבל aval top of
מ"ו עמוד א' Mem Vav Amud Aleph מועד לגמרי אם לא משכחת
בי צד תמות כלל. muad legamrei im lo meshkachas beitzad tamus klal.
If an animal is a total מועד, you know, then it’s all
a מועד. The thing it’s a מועד for is 100 percent מועד.
You don’t have a תם wrapped up within every מועד. If you
want to get an animal that’s a half תם half מועד, it’ll
only be something like a right horn and left horn. Very nice.
So that’s a push back on רב פפא בר אבא'ס Rav Pappa
bar Abba's claim of צד תמות במקומה עומדת. Okay. Last, now, top
of מ"ו עמוד א', Mem Vav Amud Aleph, last part of the
משנה. mishna. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר omer אין לו שמירה אלא
סכין. ein lo shmira ela sakin. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
for a שור מועד, shor muad, only you have to only if
you do a שחיטה shechita only if you שחט shachted it are
you exempt. Okay? You’re always going to be חייב for a שור
מועד. shor muad.
So אמר רבא amar Rava אמר רבא amar Rava מאי טעמא דרבי
אליעזר? mai taama deRabbi Eliezer? What’s the reasoning of רבי אליעזר? Rabbi
Eliezer? דאמר קרא, da’amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says ולא ישמרנו velo
yishmrenu and the owner doesn’t watch it. שוב אין לו שמירה לזה.
shuv ein lo shmira lazeh. It means that ולא ישמרנו velo yishmrenu
means it’s no longer watchable. Once a שור shor is a מועד,
then you’re either you’re always considered negligent because you can never be
considered to fully stop it from going out, and or we just
strict liability. But it sounds like once it’s a מועד, there’s always
fault. The only way you free yourself from any blame is if
you שחט shacht it. That’s what ולא ישמרנו velo yishmrenu is telling
you. אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye responds to this,
אלא מעתה דכתיב ולא יכסנו. ela me’ata dechtiv velo yichasenu. So if
that’s how we interpret the פסוק, pasuk, that it means it’s not
able anymore to be watched, so should we say the same by
a בור? bor? That it says, you know, and if somebody digs
a בור pit and doesn’t cover it, should we interpret it נמי
שוב אין לו כיסוי לזה nami shuv ein lo kisui lazeh that
now if you cover the בור pit you’re not going to be
exempt, you’re always going to be חייב? וכי תימא הכא נמי, vechi
tima hacha nami, maybe you’ll say that’s true? והתנן, vehatnan, but we
taught in a משנה, mishna, כסהו כראוי ונפל לתוכו שור או חמור
ומת פטור, kisahu karaui venafal letocho shor o chamor umet patur, that
if you covered it properly and then an animal fell in, you’d
be exempt. And we don’t hear that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer argues
on this point. So what’s the difference between the בור pit and
the שור? ox? So אלא אמר אביי ela amar Abaye says אביי,
Abaye, היינו טעמא דרבי אליעזר, hainu taama deRabbi Eliezer, this is the
reasoning of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, כדתניא kedetanya like we done in
the ברייתא, braita, רבי נתן Rabbi Natan אומר omer מנין שלא יגדל
אדם כלב רע בתוך ביתו ואל יעמיד סולם רעוע בתוך ביתו. minayin
shelo yegadel adam kelev ra betoch beiso ve’al ya’amid sulam ra’ua betoch
beiso. How do you know you shouldn’t have a bad an evil
dog in your house or a rickety ladder? That you should not
have something that’s a hazard? שנאמר shene’emar as it says ולא תשים
דמים בביתך. velo tasim damim beveitecha. You shall not have blood in
your house. And that’s about why you have to make a fence
on a roof that somebody should not fall off your house and
the blood will be on your hands, but it also means you
should not have hazards in your house that can lead to other
people to be damaged.
Okay, but what does that tell you about why you’re חייב? That
just tells you you’re not allowed to have it around. So if
you look at רש"י, Rashi רש"י Rashi says הכא נמי האי ולא
ישמרנו לא יקיימנו הוא. hacha nami hai velo yishmrenu lo yekaymenu hu.
So therefore, since it’s telling you just ולא ישמרנו, ולא יכסנו velo
yishmrenu velo yichasenu, by the בור pit or by the שור, ox,
I would say it means it’s impossible. But once I learn from
the פסוק pasuk ולא תשים דמים בביתך velo tasim damim beveitecha that
you have to get rid of it, now I’m going to say
ולא ישמרנו velo yishmrenu, that tells me that it’s not it doesn’t
mean you didn’t happen to watch it, it means since I know
anyway I gotta get rid of it, it means there’s no way
to deal with this other than to actually שחט shacht it. It’s
no longer able to be watched and you’re going to be liable.
So רש"י says it’s this obligation to get rid of it that
interacts with the פסוק pasuk ולא ישמרנו velo yishmrenu to tell you
that שמירה won’t exempt you. Of course there’s an obvious question here,
which is then say the same thing about a בור. bor. Say
a בור bor in your home is a hazard, the same way
a guarded שור ox is a hazard, and you should be obligated
to totally fill it up, you know, and why not also say
there that you’re liable? So תוספות Tosafot, deals with this and if
you look at תוספות, Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says מהאי טעמא תימה מהאי
טעמא נמי לא תשקלי בור בכיסוי משום דרבי נתן. mehai taama teima
mehai taama nami lo tiskeli bor bechisui mishum deRabbi Natan. So
why say the same thing? Okay? ויש לומר דבור אית ליה תקנתא
טפי שמתכסה כראוי משור נגח. veyesh lomar debor it lei takanta tfei
shemitkaseh karaui meshor nagach.
So the first answer תוספות Tosafot says is and you know, look,
you
an ox is a living thing so no matter how much you
watch it or guard it it’s always going to try to get
free, whereas by a covered בור bor you could say that you’ve
actually rendered it like you’ve neutralized. So if you’re not just starting
with a פסוק pasuk ולא ישמרנו velo yishmrenu ולא יכסנו, velo yichasenu
you’re starting with the idea of ולא תשים דמים בביתך, velo tasim
damim beveitecha, so an ox that’s a that’s an habitual gorer is
much more a present hazard no matter what you do than a
covered up בור bor which you could say doesn’t really even no
longer sort of exists as a בור. bor. You could also say
that the end Torah is not has to allow people to have
pits in their homes. Okay so that's תוספות'ס Tosafot's first answer. ועוד
יש לומר ve'od yesh lomar he says to make הויית סלקא דעתך
havayat salka da'atach דרבי אלעזר d'Rabbi Elazar לא יהא תשלומין קאמר. lo
yehei tashlumin ka'amar. We thought that when the משנה mishna said רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar said you had to slaughter it, that רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar meant if you don't kill it, you're בחייב be'chayav if
it damages it. אבל השתא דמסקינן טעמא דרב נתן, Aval hashta d'maskinan
ta'ama d'Rav Natan,
but now when we turn to the פסוק pasuk of לא תשים
דמים בביתך, lo tasim damim beveitecha, לאו לענין תשלומין איירי אלא לגבי
איסור בעלמא דאסור לקיימו וקאמר לגבי
בור נמי איכא. lav l'inyan tashlumin ayri, ela legabei issur b'alma de'assur
lekaymo, veka-omeir legabei bor nami ika. Okay now תוספות Tosafot says an
amazing thing. Because if you think that in the משנה, mishna, רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says אין שמירה אלא סכין. ain shemira ela sakin.
There's no way to watch it except in a knife. He never
actually said that you're going to be חייב. Okay and therefore what
the תוספות Tosafot understands is what the גמרא Gemara is saying is
that according to רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, according to רבי אלעזר, Rabbi
Elazar, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar might agree that you'll be exempt from
damages. Okay yes you do a high level of שמירה you're exempt
from damages you're not negligent etc. But the way that the Torah
still mandates that you get rid of this. Okay you might be
that you're doing enough to not be liable civilly but you have
a religious obligation or a the מצוה mitzvah is obligating you to
get rid of it and maybe the same is true about a
pit. Yes if you cover it you're exempt but you still have
to get rid of it. Again it's a little hard to imagine
that you're not allowed to have pits in your home. Okay anyway
that is how the גמרא Gemara explains רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. I
like the first answer of תוספות Tosafot actually better. The second one
is interesting, speaking that there's two levels, civil liability and an obligation
to get rid of, but the first one pointing out the difference
between a live ox cannot be totally neutralized the same way a
pit can be covered. Okay הדרן לך שור שנגח הפרה וחמשה. Hadran
lach shor shenagach hapara vechamisha. Now we take a look now we
begin the next פרק. perek. Let's take a look. שור שנגח. Shor
shenagach. Still with goring oxes. שור שנגח הפרה ונמצא עוברה בצדה. Shor
shenagach hapara venimtsa ubar betzida. An ox goes ahead and gores a
cow and you have its fetus lying by it. It was a
pregnant cow and you come and you see the ox chasing the
cow and then you look around and then you run and you
chase it and you see a gored cow with let's say the
bloody horns of the ox and you see the fetus lying next
to the cow. Okay but there's one so you can certainly have
enough evidence that he gored and you're חייב to pay. But there's
one thing you don't know. ואין ידוע אם עד שלא נגחה ילדה
אם משנגחה ילדה. Ve'ein yadua im ad shelo nagcha yalada im mishenagcha
yalada. But you don't know did the animal cow give birth first
and then it got and the goring happened
after it gave birth or did the goring happen while it was
still pregnant. And the difference is obvious. If first it gave birth
and then you have the dead fetus then the dead fetus has
no the owner of the ox has no liability for the dead
fetus. This cow gave birth to a dead fetus then my ox
gored the cow. I'm liable for the cow not for the fetus.
But if it were gored the cow while the cow was pregnant
then my ox did two things, killed the cow and and the
fetus. Okay so what do you do? Do you pay for the
fetus or not? אם משנגחה ילדה משלם חצי נזק לפרה. Im mishenagcha
yalada, meshalem chatzi nezek lapara. So you pay half damages for the
cow
because the this assuming it's a שור תם shor tam that gores.
A שור shor pays for half the damage that it caused. Half
the damage for the cow. ורביע נזק לולד. veriviva nezek lavlad. And
a quarter of the damages for the fetus. Okay why? Because
if you definitely gored the fetus you should be paying for half
the cost of the fetus. But you don't know. So this we're
going to see in the גמרא Gemara is
the this משנה'ס mishna's going like סומכוס Sumchus and סומכוס Sumchus says
ממון המוטל בספק חולקין. mamon hamutal besafek cholkin. When there's a doubt
as to whether there's a liability or not and of course the
question is how do you define what constitutes a balanced doubt? But
if there's a balanced doubt here, you know something happened, you don't
know before or after or so on, there's no way to find
out, you split the difference. Okay so had I known for sure
my ox had gored the fetus I would be paying for half
the fetus. Since I don't know for sure it's like it's 50/50,
we'll call it 50/50, I will pay for a half of the
half, I'll pay a quarter of the damages of the fetus. וכן
פרה שנגחה את השור ונמצא ולדה בצדה. Ve'chen para shenagcha et hashor
venimtza vlada betzida.
Let's say you've got a cow that is so
mad and violent that it actually successfully gored a gored a bull
okay gored an ox. The cow gored the ox. And this was
a pregnant cow. And the question here is whether was it pregnant
when it gored? And now you find the dead ox, the goring
cow, and the fetus of the cow near the cow. And the
question was did it give birth before or after the goring? ואין
ידוע אם עד שלא נגחה ילדה אם
משנגחה ילדה. Ve'ein yadua im ad shelo nagcha yalada im mishenagcha yalada.
Did it give birth before it gored and therefore you can only
collect from the cow itself right? Because remember as a תם you
can only collect up to the value... the animal itself. So if
it gave birth first and then gored, then the owner of the
ox can only collect his damages from the cow, not from the
fetus as well. Okay, so therefore what would you do? So, משתלם
חצי נזק מן הפרה ורביע נזק מן הולד. Mishtalem chatzi nezek min
haparah v'revia nezek min havlad.
The owner can collect half of his damages from the cow, and
a quarter of his damages from the fetus. Now, that doesn't seem
to make any sense. What it should say is, he could collect
his damages definitely from the cow, because the cow definitely gored,
and it's doubtful if he can collect his damages from the fetus,
so, you know, maybe if he needs still to collect from the
fetus or whatever in order to pay for the damages, maybe he
can only collect up to half the value of the fetus. That's
what you should have said. That's not what the mishna says. So
we will take a look at what how the Gemara explains the
end of the mishna. Let's take a look at the Gemara now.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, זו דברי
סומכוס. Zu divrei Sumchus. The mishna that says you split, that's the
position of Sumchus. דאמר ממון המוטל בספק חולקין. D'amar mamon hamutal besafek
cholkin. Money that is suspended in doubt, you divide, you split the
difference. And of course there's a whole discussion in the ראשונים, Rishonim,
what type of a doubt constitutes a, you know, they say it
has to be a balanced doubt, each side has to have a
legitimate claim, fine. But under certain circumstances you split it. וחכמים אומרים,
Vachachamim omrim, but the Chachamim say, זה כלל גדול בדין. Ze klal
gadol badin.
No, this is a very, the one of the most major principles
in דיני ממונות. Dinei
Mamonot. המוציא מחבירו עליו
הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah.
If you are coming to try to get somebody else to pay
up, the burden of proof is on the litigant, okay, is, you
know, is on the person bringing the suit. So if I want
to prove that you damaged me, we don't say, oh, well, 50-50
split it. I'm trying to extract money from you, I have the
burden of proof. All right, and therefore, if you can't in this
case, let's talk about the case about the ox goring the cow,
the simpler case. So, the owner of the ox says, you want
me to pay for your fetus? Prove that it was still pregnant
when I gored the cow. Since you can't prove it, I'm not
going to pay. You want me to pay, it's your burden of
proof. Okay, so now the Gemara says like this: למה לי למימר
זה כלל גדול בדין? Lamah li l'meimar ze klal gadol badin? Why
do you have to introduce it like, this is a big principle?
Why don't you just say המוציא מחבירו? Hamotzi mechavero? You know, it
seems like you're trying to say that it's such a strong principle
it applies in a wide range of cases. So what's the wide
range? אצטריך, Itzterich, you need to say that. דאפילו ניזק אומר ברי
ומזיק אומר שמא, D'afilu nizak omer bari u'mazik omer shema, המוציא מחבירו
עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah.
Even if the ניזק Nizak were to say I know that it
was still pregnant when you gored it, and the מזיק Mazik said
I don't know, maybe it was, maybe it wasn't, you still say
המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה, Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah, okay? So this means
that, you know, because there's a general discussion in the גמרא, Gemara
ברי ושמא. Bari v'Shema. Is ברי Bari preferred or not ברי Bari
preferred? I say you owe me a hundred dollars and you say
I don't know, I don't remember if I borrowed it or didn't
borrow it from you. Do we say that even with no evidence,
the strength of my definite claim is strong enough to win out
if you're not countering it with a definite claim in the opposite
direction? That's the question of ברי ושמא, Bari v'Shema, okay? And here
the גמרא Gemara is saying that if you say זה כלל גדול,
Ze klal gadol, it means that even that if you're trying to
get money from me, even if you say I definitely owe you
money and I say I don't know, maybe yes, maybe no, we
still say המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה, Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah, even though
I have not said answered your definite with a definite yes with
a definite no, you still have not brought proof, you still just
have a claim and המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah.
Now, תוספות Tosafot has whole long discussions about a lot of other
factors about when we may or may not say this true. He
introduces an idea called a ברי טוב Bari tov and a, and
a ברי גרוע Bari garua and a שמא טוב Shema tov and
a שמא גרוע. Shema garua. That like, a bad ברי Bari is
when I say you definitely owned something and you don't know, you
know, you wouldn't know if I'm lying. That's a weak ברי. Bari.
A strong ברי Bari is if you would know that I'm lying
and I say it anyway. A bad שמא Shema is when you
should know and you don't know, I don't know if I borrowed.
So ברי, Bari, if I say you borrowed a hundred dollars and
you said I don't know, that's a strong ברי Bari because you
would, you should know if I'm lying, and it's a bad שמא
Shema because, you know, you should know if it were true or
not. So that maybe, you know, ברי Bari wins. There's a, then
there's the case of a ברי גרוע, Bari garua, which is that
like, you wouldn't know if I'm lying, and a שמא טוב Shema
tov is you had no reason to know so your saying maybe
isn't, you know, isn't a weakness. So there's all those factors, other
factors as well. Anyway, whole, whole things to figure out. But the
general principle here is saying is המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה, Hamotzi mechavero
alav hara'ayah, even in case of ברי ושמא. Bari v'Shema. All right.
אי נמי. Ei nami. לכי הא דאיתמר *Leki Ha
De'itmar* or it's coming to tell you another principle that ברי ושמא
*Bari VeShema* that, excuse me, המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav
hara'aya? *Hamotzi MiChavero Alav HaRaya* applies even in the following case like
we taught. המוכר שור לחברו ונמצא נגחן *Hamocher Shor LeChavero VeNimtza Nagchan*.
Somebody sells an ox to somebody else and it turns out that
this ox has a goring nature to it and let's even say
that it was known to the owner ahead of time. Who knows.
רב אמר *Rav
Amar* הרי זה מקח טעות mekach taos. *Harei Ze Mekach
Ta'ut* that is a sale a deceptive sale, okay, a sale in
error. This person, not necessarily deceptive, might have been, but that's the
point. The point was there is an error. We can assume that
people want to buy oxen for
plowing and therefore had he known it was goring he wouldn't have
bought it so that was a material thing
that wasn't being said and therefore it was a מקח טעות mekach
taos. *Mekach Ta'ut* and he gets his money back. ושמואל אמר יכול
שיאמר לו לשחיטה מכרתיו לך uShmuel amar yachol sheyomar lo lishchita machartiv
lach *U'Shmuel Amar Yachol SheYomar Lo Lishchita Mechartiv Lecha* and שמואל *Shmuel*
says that you can say no you didn't say you wanted it
for plowing and I assumed you wanted it to you were going
to שחט *Shecht* it and you were going to turn it into
meat and therefore it's not a מקח טעות mekach taos, *Mekach Ta'ut*.
All right. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will sort of spell out
the circumstances and then we'll see how this applies to המוציא מחברו
*Hamotzi MiChavero*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמאי וניחזי אי גברא
דזבין לרדיא אי גברא דזבין לנכסתא *Amai VeNichzei Ei Gavra DeZavin LeRadya
Ei Gavra DeZavin LeNichsata*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says wait wait
a minute. Let's first try to figure out from circumstantial evidence because
it also goes to like what people had a right to expect
and so on. So is this a גברא *Gavra* that normally he's
known to be selling cows for butchers for meat or is it
a גברא *Gavra* that's normally known to be selling cows to farmers
for plowing? And once we determine that then we'll know whether it
was implicitly misrepresented or not and what the person had a right
to expect. So the גמרא *Gemara* says לא צריכא *Lo Tzricha* you
need it for the following case בגברא דזבין להכי ולהכי *BeGavra DeZavin
LeHachi U'LeHachi*. This guy will sell to farmers he'll sell to butchers
so you could infer nothing from the fact that he was selling
it. Okay so the גמרא *Gemara* says וניחזי דמי רדיא לרדיא דמי
נכסתא לנכסתא *VeNichzei Demei Radya LeRadya Demei Nichsata LeNichsata*. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says okay but let's see how much he was asking for
it. The assumption is that plowing cows
go for a higher price than cows that are going for the
slaughter. So let's look at the money and use that to determine
what the implicit assumption and understanding was. All very reasonable that you
look at those types of things. תוספות *Tosafot* has a question from
other סוגיות *Sugyot* where it doesn't seem like you pay attention to
that circumstantial evidence but the גמרא *Gemara* here is making a very
reasonable assumption that that should indicate what the presumed assumptions of the
sale were. So the גמרא *Gemara* says לא צריכא דאוקיר בישרא וקאי
בדמי רדיא *Lo Tzricha De'Okir Bisra VeKai BeDemei Radya*. Okay we're talking
about a case where actually right now the meat market is very
high cost of meat and the cow would go for the same
amount. So there was no evidence based on the type of seller
he was there was no evidence based on the price but this
guy says still I don't want a cow that I need to
slaughter I want a cow for plowing give me my money back.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says אמרי *Amri* so before we even yet
still get to המוציא מחברו *Hamotzi MiChavero* the גמרא *Gemara*'s going to
say one minute this cow now is worth the amount that you
paid for it and you just want your money back? So one
minute ואי לית ליה לאשתלומי מיניה לישקליה לתורא בזוזי *Ve'Ei Leis Lei
Le'Ishtalumi Minei Lishkaliye LeTura BeZuzei*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says like this
okay so רב *Rav* says it's a מקח טעות *Mekach Ta'ut* which
means I have to give the money back. But why can't I
if I am the seller say if I don't have the cash
on me and you want a refund I'll say okay fine give
me back the cow you want a refund oh I don't have
cash on me here I'll refund your money in cow I'll give
you the cow back. So you're once again stuck with the
cow. It's an interesting question you go to a store right you
want store credit you get your cash back
you really want the cash but will they always give you the
cash back? So the גמרא *Gemara* says דאמרי אינשי ממרי רשותך פרי
אפרע *De'Amri Inshi MiMarei Rishvatcha Parei Efra* because people say from the
person
that is in debt to you that you can you should even
be willing to accept even
dross
fodder or any type of a thing in payment. So okay I
owe money to you I have to reimburse you I'll give you
back the cow that's my payment for you if I don't have
the cash. So the גמרא *Gemara* says לא צריכא דאית ליה לאשתלומי
מיניה *Lo Tzricha De'Is Lei Le'Ishtalumi Minei* that actually I do have
cash. So if I have cash I have to give you back
cash. Okay so רב *Rav* says take back the cow give him
back the cash and שמואל *Shmuel* says no
I can still say look I assumed you wanted it for a
slaughter המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya, you prove to
me that you wanted it for something else. רב אמר הרי זה
מקח טעות, זיל בתר רובא, Rav amar hareizeh mekach taos, zil batar
ruba, because Rav's willing to go by the majority, ורובא דאינשי לרדיא
הוא דזביני veruba de'inshei leradya hu dezavini and most people sell things
for plowing and therefore it's a מקח טעות. ושמואל אמר יכול שיאמר
לו לשחיטה מכרתיו לך that you can say I sold it for
שחיטה shchita ולא אזלינן בתר רובא. velo azlinan batar ruba. Okay, period.
וכולי. vechulu. Period. Now so that's what it's coming to tell you,
it's coming to tell you that in this case you don't just
use the fact that in general the majority of people buy for
X, since there's no evidence from the case itself what the selling
was for, therefore Shmuel says it's not a מקח טעות. Now I
have to tell you that this is like, you know, like such
a different case than the earlier cases. Right? The earlier cases were
questions about like what factually happened, did the cow when did the
cow give birth? Did you borrow money or not? You're saying you
borrowed money, you're saying you don't remember, did it happen, did it
not happen? Do we say who has the burden of proof המוציא
מחברו עליו הראיה? hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya. Okay. Here, you know, it's
a question about a sale and was there a meeting of minds
or not and what did people have a right to assume or
not assume and Rav is somehow saying, you know, you have a
right to assume that unless specified otherwise this is going by what
the majority of times things are happening. And Shmuel is making a
very, you know, simple statement of like buyer beware, like no, you
know, if things aren't clear and explicit and spelled out then nobody
has any obligation to tell you and you're sort of stuck, right?
It seems anyway like a very different type of a debate than
the normal question of המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya
which is why the גמרא sort of says it's a separate point.
Okay. Now we're going to ask this question do we really say
about this point that we don't go by רוב. rov. So the
גמרא says ולא אזלינן בתר רובא? velo azlinan batar ruba? Wait a
minute. What do you mean? I thought that we always go by
רוב. rov. Oh, I'm sorry, I should pause for a second. However,
even though this case is different from the previous one, right, in
the sense that this was about a meeting of minds and a
מקח טעות, it had an additional חידוש chidush that you ignore רוב.
rov. So if you think about it we've had three cases. In
our משנה Mishna it was an equal ספק, safek, we don't say
split, we say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya In
the case where I say you borrowed a hundred dollars from me
and you say I don't know, then that there we go by
we say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya, even when
it's a ודאי vadai against a שמא. shema. And here we're going
to say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya. even in
the face of a רוב, rov, ignoring the fact of the meeting
of the minds and just sort of a simple case of רוב.
rov. We would still say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechavero alav
hara'aya. right? You could have an easier case to that if you
imagine it was a factual question. It was sixty percent likely that
the cow gave birth, you know, before rather than after. You still
wouldn't go by רוב, rov, you would say המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה.
Hamotzi Mechavero Alav Haraya, So now the גמרא says ולא אזלינן בתר
רובא, velo azlinan batar ruba, do we not go by רוב? rov?
The general principle in the תורה Torah that you go by רוב,
rov, okay, like, you know, if you want to know is this
a kosher piece of meat, not a kosher piece of meat, all
these different types of questions that you say, you know, you go
by רוב. rov. So the גמרא says הני מילי כי אזלינן בתר
רובא באיסורא. hanei milei ki azlinan batar ruba be'isura. That's to determine
like the הלכה halacha status of something. אבל בממונא, aval bemamona, when
it comes to money, לא אזלינן בתר רובא, lo azlinan batar ruba,
אלא המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, ela hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya, you have
the burden of proof. Okay, which means that right, you do go
by רוב rov when you don't know let's say the status of
this piece of meat, did I buy it from a כשר kosher
store, not כשר kosher store? If there were nine כשר kosher and
one not כשר, kosher, you know, questions like that, you assume it
came from the majority and
but that's when you want to know the status of something and
it's in doubt so you assume it's status based on the majority.
Here it's about, you know, litigants. You want me to pay you
money, so you're coming to me and trying to extract money from
me, you have a burden of proof, and רוב rov doesn't satisfy
the burden of proof. Okay. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, now
we taught similarly that our משנה's Mishna going like סומכוס Sumchus and
that the חכמים Chachamim disagree, going back to that first point that
it was סומכוס Sumchus and the חכמים Chachamim say המוציא מחברו עליו
הראיה. Hamotzi Mechavero Alav Haraya. שור שנגח את הפרה ונמצא עוברה בצדה,
Shor shenagach es hapara venimtza ubra betzida, an ox gored a cow
and you found the fetus by itself, ואינו ידוע אם עד שלא
נגחה ילדה אם משנגחה ילדה, ve'eino yadu'a im ad shelo negacha yalda
im mishenegacha yalda, you don't know if it was if it gave
birth before or after it was gored, משלם חצי נזק לפרה ורביע
נזק לולד, meshalem chatzi nezek lapara urevih nezek lavalad, you pay half
damages for the cow because it definitely gored the cow, and a
quarter for the fetus, it maybe gored the fetus, so the you
split it, it should have been half but it's a half of
a half, it's a quarter. דברי סומכוס, divrei Sumchus, says Sumchus, וחכמים
אומרים המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. veChachamim omrim hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya.
Okay. So there it's very clear that that's a debate of סומכוס
Sumchus and the חכמים. Chachamim. אמר רב שמואל בר נחמני, Amar Rav
Shmuel bar Nachmani, says Shmuel bar Nachmani... Said שמואל בר נחמני *Shmuel
bar Nachmani*. מניין להמוציא מחברו עליו הראיה *Minayin lehamotzi mechavero alav haraya*?
Where do you know this principle from? That you have the burden
of proof? שנאמר *Shene'emar*, the פסוק *pasuk* says, מי בעל דברים יגש
אליהם *Mi ba’al devarim yigash aleihem*. Moshe says, I'm going up to
Har Sinai, I'm leaving Aaron and Chur, whoever has a matter, you
come to them. So what does it mean? יגיש ראיה Raya, אליהם
*Yagish raya aleihem* that if you want to go ahead and you
have you're the litigant, you know, you're the guy that's making the
claim, you have to produce the evidence. If you want to win
now, you have a בעל דברים *ba'al devarim*, you're trying to demand
something from somebody else, you have to produce the evidence. Okay, מתקיף
לה רב אשי *Maskif lei Rav Ashi*. Rav Ashi challenges. הלא למה
לי קרא סברא הוא *Halamah li kra sevara hu*. Why do I
need a פסוק *pasuk*? It's סברא *sevara*. By the way, that idea
itself is, you know, for some, some people point out how powerful
that is. You know, the sort of the power of like the
sort of, you know, the human the human element of תורה שבעל
פה *Torah she-be'al peh* and the, you know, the rational sort of
power of of just the rational thought is that that a פסוק
*pasuk* is not weightier than something I could have known just from
סברא *sevara*. Why do I need a פסוק *pasuk*? I could have
I knew it anyway from סברא *sevara*. That I knew it anyway
logically. דכאיב ליה כאבי אזיל לבי אסיא *Dekhaiv leih keivi azil levei
asya*. The guy who has the pain, he's the one that has
to go to the doctor. Okay,
so if you're the one that you want to collect and you're
the one that's the litigant, you're the one that has the responsibility
to, you know, to bring the proof. Now, it's a little funny
because you could say, yeah, I mean you got to go to
the doctor, fine. Like, you know, the guy who I'm suing isn't
going to court, I'm the one who's going to court. Okay, but
does that exactly make the statement that I have the burden of
proof? Once I'm suing him and it's in court, maybe we should
sort of say, I don't know, split it if there's evidence both
ways, right? So it's not exactly clear why he feels that you
don't need a פסוק *pasuk* to teach you this principle, but anyway.
אלא קרא *Ella kra*, the פסוק *pasuk* for him, so he thinks
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה Hamotzi Mechavero Alav Haraya *hamotzi mechavero alav haraya*
you know from סברא *sevara*. So what's the פסוק *pasuk* telling you?
לכדרב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה *Likhdirav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha*.
דאמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה *De-amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah
bar Avuha*, like the teaching of Rav Nachman in the name of
Rabbah bar Avuha. מניין שנזקקין לתובע תחילה *Minayin shenizkakim letoveiah techila*? How
do you know that if you have somebody that is, you know,
suing and somebody else is a countersuit, how do you know that
you first deal with the suit and only afterwards do you deal
with the countersuit? שנאמר *Shene'emar*, כי מי בעל דברים יגש אליהם *Ki
mi ba’al devarim yigash aleihem*. יגיש דבריו אליהם *Yagish devarav aleihem*. The
person who has the matter, who pushes the matter, he's the one
that sort of comes first and and presents it first. אמרי מנהרדעא
*Amri min Neharde'a*, says Neharde'a, פעמים שנזקקין לנתבע תחילה *Pe'amim shenizkakim lenitba
techila*. There are times when actually you would first attend to the
one being sued who then made a countersuit. Why? והיכי דמי דחזינן
לנכסיה *Ve-heichi dami de-chazinan lenikhseih*. Let's say that his property is being
devalued because you have to go to the, you know, deal with
the suit the person who brought the suit, you're dealing with that
suit first and in the meantime this person is being pressured because
he has creditors and because he's not able to deal with his
countersuit his creditors are taking advantage of the situation and he's having
to like, you know, discount the value of his property. In that
type of a case where he's losing out by going to him
second, you would deal with him first. All right, fine. So that's
the basic point though. You first deal with the suit and then
the countersuit. Of course, there's a big debate about רש"י *Rashi* and
תוספות *Tosafot*. How do you define what's the suit and what's the
countersuit, right? I mean just because I produced it second means that
I'm the נתבע *nitba* and he's the תובע *toveiah*? You know, maybe
my countersuit is is just as much as I'm the בעל דברים
*ba'al devarim* and he's you know in my countersuit I'm the תובע
*toveiah* and he's the נתבע *nitba*. So it's not exact I mean
there's it's not exactly clear how exactly you categorize this, but the
basic principle we understand. Okay, now we move to the second part
of the משנה mishna *Mishna*, the hard part to understand. וכן פרה
שנגחה שור *Vekhein parah shenagcha shor*.
The cow gored the ox, and you don't know if it had
the fetus in it or it didn't have the fetus in it.
So what it should have said is you can collect so you
collect half of the damages of the ox, half damages of the
damaged thing, and you can collect from the whole cow is there
to collect from, and half of the fetus is available to collect
from. That's what you should have said, but that's not what the
משנה mishna *Mishna* says. The משנה mishna. *Mishna* says, חצי נזק chatzi
nezek ורביע נזק urevia nezek. *chatzi nezek u-reviah nezek*. Half damages from
the cow and a quarter damages from the fetus. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says, חצי נזק chatzi nezek, ורביע נזק urevia nezek. *chatzi nezek
u-reviah nezek*? What do you mean half damages and a quarter damages?
First of all, that sounds like you're going to collect three-quarters damages.
That's not true. פלגא נזקא הוא דבעי שלומי *Palga nizka hu de-ba’ei
shalumei*. So you
you you're only entitled to collect half damages. כולי נזקא נכי רביע
מאי עבידתיה *Kulei nizka nekhei reviah mai avidteih*? Full minus a quarter,
three-quarters damages, since when did you get a right to collect three-quarters
damages, which is what the משנה mishna. *Mishna* sounds like. So אמר
אביי Amar Abaye, חצי נזק chatzi nezek, אחד מארבע בנזק echad me'arba
banezek. ורביע נזק urevia nezek אחד משמונה בנזק echad mishmona banezek, *Amar
Abaye chatzi nezek echad me-arba be-nezek u-reviah nezek echad mi-shmoneh be-nezek*. So
אביי Abaye *Abaye* says what it means is half of the half
and a quarter of the half. Okay, so what it means is
is that you are he's like let's assume the Let's assume the
following case. Let's assume that the cow gored the ox, and the
ox was worth 200. So you have a right to collect 100.
Now we're going to assume that the fetus is an equal gorer
to the ox to the you know as the cow. The cow
with its fetus gored, and תוספות says that we're just doing this
for simplicity sake. Obviously we would figure it out proportionally. But let's
assume that we decided who who like you know who gored by
their weight. So you know let's say the cow was worth was
weighed 90 pounds and the fetus weighed 10 pounds we would and
we saw them as two gorers they were all combined in this
one animal of the cow but they were two things doing the
goring. So you would collect 90 percent from the cow and 10
percent from the fetus. Somehow you would divide it proportionally. But for
simplicity sake we're going to say call it 50/50. The משנה Mishna.
is sort of dealing with that as an as-if. Okay? So here
I am I have a dead ox 200 I'm entitled to collect
100. I have two things that gored me, assuming the fetus was
in the cow. The cow and the fetus. So I can collect
my 100, 50 from the cow, 50 from the fetus. That's what
I would do if I knew the fetus was there. Since I
don't know that the fetus was there, I only collect 25 from
the fetus. So I'm going to collect 50 from the cow and
25 from the fetus. That's what the משנה is telling you. Okay
so which means that you look at them as equal gorers and
you divide, not meaning or proportional, but for simplicity we're going to
call it equal and you divide. You can only collect you know
half of the damages you're entitled to which is half of a
half. You're entitled to half of your 200, 100. Half of that
half you can collect from the cow. That's when it says חצי
נזק from the cow, half of your half, and you can collect
the other half from the fetus, but only not really half, only
a quarter because of ממון המוטל בספק. maman hamutal besafek. So that's
going to be a quarter of your half. Okay so that's how
it's going to work out. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, חצי נזק, אחד
מארבע בנזק. echad me'arba banezek. It really means a quarter. It means
half of what you were entitled the damages you were entitled to
which started off being half. Okay so half of what you're entitled
to. ורביע נזק. Okay so and ורביע נזק. So let's do that
again. So אמר אביי, Abaye חצי נזק, אחד מארבע בנזק.
So half damages really means a quarter, it means half of the
half you're entitled to. ורביע נזק and a quarter means אחד משמונה
בנזק, an eighth, a quarter of what you're entitled to. Okay which
is not a bad read of the משנה. Okay so basically
whatever you're entitled to because of your dead ox, half of it
you get from the cow and a quarter of it you get
from the fetus. That's easy enough, fine. ואי פרה וולד דחד נינהו,
Ve'i paru vavlad dechad ninhu,
now if the cow and the and the fetus all belong to
the same owner, right? You could sell the fetus within the cow,
but assuming that you didn't, they all belong to the same owner,
הכא נמי דמצי אמר ליה לבעל פרה ממנפשך חצי נזק הב לי.
hacha nami d'matzi amar lei l'ba'al paru mimah nafshach chatzi nezek hav
li.
Then I wouldn't consider it two gorers. This is all your one
big cow. I see it as one big gorer. And I'm going
to collect my full damages from the cow. I don't have to
split it between the cow and the fetus. Think of the fetus
as a leg. Right? You don't have to tell me oh I
have to take 10 percent from this leg and 10 percent from
that leg or whatever. I'm entitled to take it from whichever part
of this animal gored. So fine, if you own both the cow
and the fetus, I'll collect my full half damages from the cow.
I don't have to split it between the two. So that can't
be what's going on in the משנה. אלא לא צריכא דפרה דחד
וולד דחד. Ela lo tzericha d'paru dechad vavlad dechad.
No the case is I sold the fetus, the fetus you know
was sold to a different person. Shimon owns the cow Reuven owns
the cow and Shimon owns the fetus. And therefore you know
therefore it's not fair to take it from one and not the
other. I do have to split it. So I take half from
Reuven, half from Shimon, again assuming that we're going to treat the
ולד vlad as if it did half the damage, which תוספות says
really means proportional. So from Reuven I get the full half of
the damages I'm entitled to, half of the half, and from Shimon
I only get a quarter. Okay so now the גמרא says like
this. ואי דקדים תבעי לבעל פרה תחילה, Ve'i dekadim tavei leba'al paru
techila,
so the גמרא says one minute. But if you went ahead and
first you know went to the cow owner of the cow, to
Reuven, and you got your half, הכא נמי דאמר ליה לבעל פרה
פרה דיזק אזקתך הב לי ראיה דאית לך שותפי. hacha nami de'amar
lei leba'al paru paru dizak izkatach hav li raya d'it lach shutafi.
So he says if that were true in that scenario,
Reuven owned the cow Shimon owned the fetus and they gored me
and now I have to decide where I'm going to collect my
100 dollars from, which is half of the damages, why don't I
start by going to Reuven and saying Reuven I know your cow
gored me. Therefore, and you know your cow gored me. We have
evidence of that. Therefore
It's questionable if שמעון Shimon was involved in it. Maybe the cow
gave birth beforehand. Okay, so you're definitely obligated to me, and if
you want to get off and put half of that obligation on
שמעון, Shimon, you have a responsibility to prove that שמעון Shimon was
there. And since you can't, I'm entitled to collect fully from you.
Okay, so that's what the גמרא assumes, you know, it's a little
question how does that fit into like המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, but
anyway, but here we're dealing with סומכוס, Sumchos, סומכוס Sumchos doesn't hold
of המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. And also there's a ודאי חיוב Vadai
Chiyuv here and you're trying to get out of the חיוב. Chiyuv.
אלא דקדים תבע לבעל ולד תחילה, Ella Dekadim Tavei Lebaal Vlad Techilla,
it must be that I first went to שמעון. Shimon. And I
said שמעון, Shimon, I think you were involved. Give me half. And
שמעון Shimon says, no, it gave birth first. So we say, okay,
we'll split it. I'll take a quarter from you. Then I go
to ראובן Reuven and ראובן Reuven says, דאמר ליה גלית דעתך דשותפא
אית לי, Damar Lei Galit Daatach Deshutfa Is Lei, you went to
שמעון, Shimon, you showed that you think that you already concede that
שמעון Shimon was involved. You're claiming שמעון Shimon was involved, you collected
a quarter from שמעון, Shimon, so now you're only entitled to collect
the remaining half from me. Okay. איכא דאמרי, Ika Deamri, so that's
one way of interpreting it. So what אביי said is half and
a quarter don't mean half of the 200 damages, it means half
of what I'm entitled to. Half of what I'm entitled to I
get from the cow and a quarter of what I'm entitled to
I get from the fetus. That works if they're separate owners, then
I have to deal with them separately and by the fetus we
say ממון המוטל בספק חולקין, Mamon Hamutal Besafek Cholkin, but that would
only be when I go to the owner of the fetus first,
otherwise I would be entitled to say to to ראובן, Reuven, the
owner of the cow, prove to me that שמעון Shimon was involved.
איכא דאמרי, Ika Deamri, some say אף על גב דקדים תבע לבעל
פרה תחילה, Af Al Gav Dekadim Tavei Lebaal Para Techilla, no, maybe
even if I did go to ראובן Reuven first, מצי מדחי ליה.
Matzi Madchei Lei. No, but ראובן Reuven could still get out of
it, דאמר ליה מידע ידעי דשותפא אית לי, Damar Lei Meida Yadai
Deshutfa Is Lei, I know that שמעון Shimon was involved, you know,
so you don't have a ראיה, you know, to demand from me
that I pay you more than half. Okay, being sort of like
getting into the המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה type of a thing. I
know I, yes, I damaged you, but you can't, you can't prove
that I was involved in more than half of the damage, so
I'm only going to pay you half. Okay, so we will end
with this. This is אביי's explanation and then we will see tomorrow
that רבא Rava will give it a very, very
different read of the משנה.